Eva vom Baur Hansl Collection of Women's Vocational Materials
Eva vom Baur Hansl Collection of Women's Vocational Materials
1927-1967
Hansl, Eva vB. (Eva vom Baur).
24 linear ft.
Extensive collection of materials relating to the education, employment, marital status, and intellectual life of women in society. Material encompasses women in the U.S. as well as in other countries. Topics include education, careers, roles and attitudes, family issues (marriage, divorce, children, home management), well-known women, working women, and many other subjects. Collected by Eva vom Baur Hansl, American author, journalist, radio producer, and lecturer.
2629839
Biographical History
Eva Elise vom Baur Hansl, woman's editor and pioneer in women's radio broadcasting, was born to Elise Urchs and Carl Max vom Baur on 29 Jan 1889 in New York City, the youngest of five daughters and a son. She attended the New York Collegiate Institute and after graduating from Barnard College in 1909 became a member of the Intercollegiate Bureau of Occupations, one of the earliest organizations concerned with employment for women. From 1911-1916 she reported the progress of the early feminist movement for the New York Tribune and the New York Evening Sun; at the latter she was editor of the women's page from 1912-1916. In 1915-1916 she directed a course of public lectures at New York University on vocations for women, and from 1916-1918 she organized the League for Women's Vocational Opportunities. She was an associate editor of Parents magazine and organized play-schools and parents' study groups in Princeton and Summit, New Jersey and in Greenwich, Connecticut.
In 1916 she married Raleigh Hansl, from whom she was later divorced. When her two children, Barbara and Raleigh, were grown, she returned to journalism with the Education Department of the New York Times. Her efforts on behalf of the education and employment of women continued for the next four decades. In 1936 she founded Trend-File, a reference service on women's interests and activities, which she maintained for many years. Her long interest in women's activities led to broadcasting when she supervised the research, promotion, and production of three network radio series: "Women in the Making of America" and "Gallant American Women"for NBC, in cooperation with the U.S. Office of Education (1939-1940), and "Womanpower," for CBS in cooperation with the War Manpower Commission (1942-1943).
In 1941 Hansl left New York City to work in Washington with the War Manpower Commission, but after that returned to New York City which remained her home for the rest of her life. From 1947-1950 she was a member of the committee of the World Center for Women's Archives, Inc. in New York City. She lectured at New York University and Columbia University, and wrote several books including Minute sketches of great composers (1931), Artists in music today (1933), Trends in part-time employment of college trained women (1949), and many articles in popular periodicals.
Eva vB Hansl died on 11 Apr 1978.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Eva vom Baur Hansl Collection of Women's Vocational Materials comprises materials relating to the education, employment, marital status, and intellectual life of women in society. The material encompasses women in the U.S. as well as in other countries, and topics include education, careers, roles and attitudes, family issues (marriage, divorce, children, home management), well-known women, working women, and many other subjects. The material is divided into 15 series.
Conferences contains material from conferences on children, education, home and family, labor, and other topics.
Continuing Education material relates to projects at more than 40 American universities.
Education covers all aspects of women's education, including coeducation, community colleges, counseling, curriculum, drop-outs, Head Start, home study, legislation, middle-aged women returning to school, older women workers, teaching, and much more.
England includes topics such as British women in the war, as well as material relating to the British Federation of University Women and the International Federation of University Women.
The History of women's education includes an outline for "Women's Education Begins" as well as pro and con views of feminism and other articles and book reviews.
A large collection of material relating to Home and Family comprises topics such as adoption, birth rates, budgets, child care, women as consumers, dual-job situations, education, health, home economics, migrant families, mothers and daughters, nursing homes, widows, and many more.
International and Foreign Women covers more than 25 countries and also contains material relating to the United Nations and some miscellaneous clippings.
Occupations and counseling encompasses a broad range of careers, not limited to those traditionally ascribed to women. Everything from architecture to veterinary medicine is represented.
Part time employment focuses on the particular challenges and opportunities for part-time working women, and includes case histories, surveys, questionnaires, and much more.
Roles and attitudes towards women, particularly working women, looks at psychological aspects, mass media representations, social tensions, and similar questions.
War Years focuses on the activities of women during World War I and World War II. Topics found here include case histories, civilian women leaders, housing, African-American women (Ms. Hansl's original folder titles have been retained hence the use of the term "Negro"), women as peace advocates, labor shortages, the G.I Bill of Rights, and numerous others.
Womanpower looks specifically at issues of interest to women in the workplace, such as earnings and education, the Civil Rights Act, women as business owners or managers, equal pay, maternity benefits, recruitment of women, working mothers, and more.
General files cover a wide range of topics from affluence and alcohol through grandmothers and horticulture to youth power. Published Material contains newspaper clippings on a similarly wide range of topics.
A small amount of Miscellaneous unsorted material completes the collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
All series are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
See also the
Eva vom Baur Hansl Papers
, which contain material relating to Hansl's own career and particularly her radio broadcasts in the 1930s and 1940s.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Popular culture; Radio, television, film; Women Authors; Hansl, Eva vB. (Eva vom Baur) -- Archives.; Federal Theatre Project (U.S.); United States. -- Office of Education.; United States. -- War Manpower Commission.; United States. -- Works Progress Administration.; Gallant American women (Radio program); Womanpower (Radio program); Women in the making of America (Radio program); Adult education -- United States.; Documentary radio programs.; Feminism -- Archival resources.; Feminists -- United States.; German Americans.; Housewives -- United States.; Professional education of women.; Radio authorship.; Radio programs.; Radio producers and directors -- United States.; Radio scripts -- Specimens.; Women -- Biography.; Women -- Education.; Women -- Education (Higher); Women -- Employment.; Women -- History -- Archival resources.; Women -- Intellectual life.; Women -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Women in politics.; Women -- Social conditions.; Women -- Vocational education.; Women -- United States.; Women in radio broadcasting.; Women authors, American.; Women in the mass media industry.; Women journalists -- United States.; Women's mass media.; Women's rights -- United States.; Women's studies -- Archival resources.; Bibliographies.; Biographies.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Pamphlets.; Radio scripts.; Speeches (documents); Surveys (documents); Authors.; Feminists.; Journalists.; Lecturers.; Radio producers and directors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Background
  - Outline of the Eva vB. Hansl Collection, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Foreword to the Eva vB. Hansl Collection (Box 1)
  - Foreword, partial revised draft, Dec 1968 (Box 1)
  - Foreword guide
    - Outlines (Box 1)
    - "Slump and Spark" (Box 1)
  - Postcripts to the collection, Dec 1968 (Box 1)
  - Trend file
    - Description of services (Box 1)
    - Index, 1937-1939 (Box 1)
- Conferences
  - Outline (Box 1)
  - General (Box 1)
  - Career Opportunity and Plans, 1960; 1963,; 1965; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Children in a democracy, White House Conference on, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Education, 1961-1963; 1965; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Home and Family, 1948; 1965; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Labor, 1959-1967; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - On Women, 1960-1963; 1966-1967,; undated; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Continuing Education
  - Index (Box 2)
  - General (Box 2)
  - College programs (Box 2)
  - Prelude to Continuing Education (Box 2)
  - Programs at colleges and universities
    - University of Akron (Box 2)
    - Archdiocese of Detroit Institute (Box 2)
    - Barnard College (Box 2)
    - Bennington College (Box 2)
    - Boston University (Box 2)
    - Briarcliff College (Box 2)
    - University of California, Berkeley (Box 2)
    - University of Colorado (Box 2)
    - Cornell University (Box 2)
    - Douglass College of Rutgers University (Box 2)
    - Fairleigh-Dickinson University (Box 2)
    - Florida State University (Box 2)
    - George Washington University (Box 2)
    - Goddard College (Box 2)
    - Indiana University (Box 2)
    - Johns Hopkins University (Box 2)
    - University of Kansas City (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan (Box 2)
    - University of Minnesota (Box 2)
    - Mount Holyoke College (Box 2)
    - Mundelein College (Box 2)
    - New School Social Research (New York City) (Box 2)
    - State University of New York (Box 2)
    - New York University (Box 2)
    - Northeastern University (Boston, Mass.) (Box 2)
    - Oakland University (Box 2)
    - Ohio State University (Box 2)
    - University of Oklahoma (Box 2)
    - Pennsylvania College for Women (Box 2)
    - University of Pennsylvania (Box 2)
    - University of Pittsburgh (Box 2)
    - Purdue University (Box 2)
    - Radcliffe College (Box 2)
    - Rutgers University (Box 2)
    - Sarah Lawrence College (Box 2)
    - Simmons College (Box 2)
    - Southern Methodist University, Dallas College (Box 2)
    - Stephens College (Box 2)
    - Syracuse University (Box 2)
    - Vassar College (Box 2)
    - University of Washington (Box 2)
    - Webster College (Box 2)
    - Wellesley College (Box 2)
    - University of Wisconsin (Box 2)
    - Yeshiva University (Box 2)
  - Programs for women at various institutions, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Study and continuity (Box 2)
- Education
  - Index (Box 3)
  - General, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Accreditation, adult education (Box 3)
  - Alumnae Surveys (Box 3)
  - Bibliography (Box 3)
  - Campus marriages, career counseling, A. Heywood, career planning, "catalyst" (Box 3)
  - Certification, child development, clippings, 1944-1966 (Box 4)
  - Coeducation, community colleges (Box 4)
  - Community Junior College (Box 4)
  - Community resources for counseling (Box 4)
  - Cooperative education (Box 4)
  - Costs (Box 4)
  - Counseling and educational television (Box 4)
  - Counseling center (Box 4)
  - Counseling for college women (Box 4)
  - Curriculum, college (Box 4)
  - Degrees (Box 4)
  - Discontinuities (Box 4)
  - Discrimination (Box 4)
  - Doctorates (PhD's and EdD's) (Box 4)
  - Doctorate holders (Box 4)
  - Drop-outs (Box 4)
  - Drop-outs, educational (Box 4)
  - Education for counseling (Box 4)
  - Equivalency (Box 4)
  - Experiments (Box 4)
  - Facts and figures (Box 4)
  - Financing (Box 4)
  - Funds and scholarships (Box 4)
  - Future (Box 4)
  - Graduate work (Box 4)
  - Head Start project (Box 4)
  - Higher education (Box 4)
  - Higher education, doctorate degrees (Box 4)
  - Home study courses (Box 4)
  - Illiteracy (Box 4)
  - Industrial sponsorship of college graduates (Box 4)
  - Job horizons for women - New York State (Box 4)
  - Legislation (Box 4)
  - Management education (Box 4)
  - Marriage (Box 4)
  - Marriage and career (Box 4)
  - Middle-aged women (Box 4)
  - Middle years, counseling and workshops (Box 4)
  - Migrant children (Box 4)
  - Motivation (Box 4)
  - Negro education (Box 4)
  - Non-college bound student (Box 4)
  - Nursing profession (Box 4)
  - Obstacles for women (Box 4)
  - Obstacle removers (Box 4)
  - Occupations, miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Older workers, education and counseling (Box 4)
  - Organizations (Box 4)
  - Parent survey of education in the United States (Box 4)
  - Partnership Teaching Program (Box 4)
  - Patterns in careers for women, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Physical sciences, "Role of Women's Colleges in the Physical Sciences" (conference), Bryn Mawr, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Publications on women's education (Box 5)
  - Quality of education (Box 5)
  - Refresher courses and retraining (Box 5)
  - Research (Box 5)
  - Retarded children (Box 5)
  - Retirement: "It's never too late" (Box 5)
  - Scholarships and fellowships (Box 5)
  - Science
    - Careers, general (Box 5)
    - Careers as science writers (Box 5)
  - Sex education (Box 5)
  - Social work
    - Career data and related information (Box 5)
    - Part-time (Box 5)
  - "Southern college women," Fred Schab (Box 5)
  - Student unrest (Box 5)
  - Superior student (Box 5)
  - Talent search (Box 5)
  - Teacher's College at Columbia University, "New course on vocations for girls and women", 1918 (Box 5)
  - Teaching
    - General (Box 5)
    - Profession (Box 5)
    - Substitute teaching (Box 5)
  - Tests (Box 5)
  - Unskilled jobs (Box 5)
  - Vocational guidance (Box 5)
  - Wastage (Box 5)
  - Women's colleges, status of (Eva vB Hansl) (Box 5)
  - Workshops (Box 5)
  - Education, miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Counseling, miscellaneous (Box 5)
- England
  - General, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Bibliographies, Fawcett Society (Box 5)
  - British Federation of University Women, Ltd. (Box 5)
  - Clippings (Box 5)
  - Homecraft Course at Oxford (Box 5)
  - Pamphlets - women and work (Box 5)
  - Part-time jobs (Box 5)
  - Reports (Box 5)
  - Social forces (Box 5)
  - War years
    - British women in the war (Box 5)
    - Education and jobs (Box 5)
  - Women in higher education, International Federation of University Women, 2 folders (Box 6)
- History
  - Outline (Box 6)
  - General (Box 6)
  - American Women's Heritage, The (Box 6)
  - Articles and book reviews (Box 6)
  - Brown University (Box 6)
  - Feminism: Views for and Against (Box 6)
  - Women in history (Box 6)
  - 1930s (Box 6)
  - "Women's Education Begins" outline (Box 6)
- Home and Family
  - Abortion (Box 7)
  - Adoption (Box 7)
  - Allowances (Box 7)
  - The Anonymous Women (Box 7)
  - Attitudes (Box 7)
  - Automation and the homemaker (Box 7)
  - Babies and birthrate (Box 7)
  - Babiess, prenatal stage (Box 7)
  - Baby sitters (Box 7)
  - Bibliographies (Box 7)
  - Birth control (Box 7)
  - Budget (Box 7)
  - Careers - homemaking (Box 7)
  - Case histories: How they manage (Box 7)
  - Child care (Box 7)
    See also Day care
  - Child care centers (Box 7)
  - Child Care International (Box 7)
  - Child care legislation (Box 7)
  - Child welfare (Box 7)
  - Childhood (Box 7)
  - Children, dependent and neglected (Box 7)
  - Children, migrant (Box 7)
  - Children, quotes (Box 7)
  - Children of working mothers (Box 7)
  - Community affairs (Box 7)
  - Community child care (Box 7)
  - Community volunteers (Box 7)
  - Consumer (Box 7)
  - Cost of living (Box 7)
  - Day care (Box 7)
    See also Child care
  - Day care, general articles, conference projects (Box 7)
  - Day care organizations (Box 7)
  - Divorce, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Dual Job
    - "The Economics of the Family in a Democracy" (Box 7)
    - Home management (Box 7)
    - Hancock Conference (Box 7)
    - How Do they Manage? (Box 7)
    - Hunter College Conference, 1957 (Box 7)
    - Problems for women (Box 7)
    - Surveys and studies (Box 7)
    - Home management training (Box 7)
  - Dual Job II
    - Homemaker education (Box 7)
  - Dual Job III
    - Time and motion (Box 7)
  - Economic Problems of the Family (Box 8)
  - Education and Counseling (Box 8)
  - Family, general, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Family Care Projects for Working Women (Box 8)
  - The Family Cycle, 1947 (Box 8)
  - Family, role of (Box 8)
  - Foster care (Box 8)
  - Gifted pre-school children (Box 8)
  - Government aid (Box 8)
  - Grandmothers (Box 8)
  - Growth and development of children, Myrtle McGran (Box 8)
  - Heads of families, women as (Box 8)
  - Health in the home (Box 8)
  - Home and family (Box 8)
  - Home economics (Box 8)
  - Home economics counseling for homemakers (Box 8)
  - Home Economic Association Journal, History of (Box 8)
  - Home related activities (Box 8)
  - Homemakers
    - General (Box 8)
    - Handicapped (Box 8)
    - Services, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Skills (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Homemaking aids (equipment) (Box 8)
  - Household employees, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Housing
    - General (Box 8)
    - Literature on (Box 8)
  - Husbands, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Income, family (Box 8)
  - Juvenile delinquency (Box 8)
  - Labor, family (Box 9)
  - Law, family (Box 9)
  - Leisure for housewives (Box 9)
  - Management, problems of homemakers outside the home (Box 9)
  - Marriage (Box 9)
  - Married Women's Association (Box 9)
  - Migrant families (Box 9)
  - Mothers (Box 9)
    - Young (Box 9)
    - Role (Box 9)
    - Working (Box 9)
  - National Conference on Family Life, 1948; news stories (Box 9)
  - National policy re: the family (Box 9)
  - Nursery education (Box 9)
  - Nursery school (Box 9)
  - Nursing homes (Box 9)
  - Nutrition (Box 10)
  - Orphans (Box 10)
    See Widows
  - Parents (Box 10)
  - Parents Without Partners (Box 10)
  - Planning, family (Box 10)
  - Rehabilitation (Box 10)
  - Research on family life (Box 10)
  - Rural women (Box 10)
  - Sex (Box 10)
  - Support (Box 10)
  - Time management (Box 10)
  - Time, saving (Box 10)
  - Time, work and leisure (Box 10)
  - Unwed (Box 10)
  - Volunteer workers and associations (Box 10)
  - Widows, 2 folders (Box 10)
    See also Orphans
  - Wives (Box 10)
  - Work cycles (Box 10)
- International and Foreign Women
  - Index, partial (Box 10)
  - American women workers (Box 10)
  - American - Soviet relationships (Box 10)
  - Belgian women (Box 10)
  - Canada, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - China (Box 10)
  - Congress of American Women (Box 10)
  - Cuba (Box 10)
  - Czechoslovakia (Box 10)
  - Egypt (Box 10)
  - England (Box 10)
  - France (Box 10)
  - Germany, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Holland, general (Box 10)
  - India (Box 10)
  - International publications on women (Box 11)
  - Iran (Box 11)
  - Ireland (Box 11)
  - Israel (Box 11)
  - Italy (Box 11)
  - Japan (Box 11)
  - Latin America (Box 11)
  - Poland (Box 11)
  - Puerto Rico (Box 11)
  - Romania (Box 11)
  - Sicily (Box 11)
  - Soviet Union
    - Education, social security (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
  - Sweden (Box 11)
  - Switzerland (Box 11)
  - United Nations
    See also General files: United Nations
    - Foreign women (Box 11)
    - International publications on women (Box 11)
    - Publications, general (Box 11)
    - Publications on women (Box 11)
    - Studies and reports on women (Box 11)
    - UNESCO (Box 11)
  - Vietnam (Box 11)
  - "Women Speaking" publications (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 11)
- Occupations and counseling
  - General (Box 11)
  - General, women (Box 11)
  - Actresses (Box 11)
  - Advertising (Box 11)
  - Age (Box 11)
  - Agriculture, women in (Box 11)
  - Architecture (Box 11)
  - Armed Forces (Box 11)
  - Arts - ballet (Box 11)
  - Atomic energy (Box 11)
  - Atomic energy (Box 11)
  - Aviation, women in (Box 11)
  - Bankers, women as (Box 11)
  - Beauty as a business (Box 11)
  - Blue collar (Box 11)
  - Career for women (Box 11)
  - Case histories (Box 11)
  - Computers (Box 11)
  - Dance (Box 11)
  - Design, women in (Box 11)
  - Dietetics and nutrition (Box 11)
  - Economics (Box 11)
  - Education, women in (Box 11)
  - Engineering, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Executives (Box 12)
  - Fashions as business (Box 12)
  - Federal service, women in (Box 12)
  - Financiers, women as (Box 12)
  - Government, women in (Box 12)
  - Health careers, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Historians, women as (Box 12)
  - Home economics (Box 12)
  - Industrial arts, women in (Box 12)
  - Insurance (Box 12)
  - Inventors (Box 12)
  - Journalism, general (Box 12)
  - Landscape architecture. women in (Box 12)
  - Languages (Box 12)
  - Law (Box 12)
  - Librarians, women as (Box 12)
  - Libraries, general (Box 12)
  - Library profession (Box 13)
  - Library, public, inquiry by Social Science Research Council, 1948 (Box 13)
  - Libraries, shortages in (Box 13)
  - Mass Media (television, radio) (Box 13)
  - Mathematicians, women, in industry (Box 13)
  - Medical careers (Box 13)
  - Medicine (Box 13)
  - Medicine, women in (Box 13)
  - Meteorology (Box 13)
  - Music (Box 13)
  - Nuns (Box 13)
  - Nurses
    - Clippings (Box 13)
    - Index (Box 13)
    - Notes (Box 13)
  - Nursing
    - Age (New York City) (Box 13)
    - Bibliography (Box 13)
    - Case histories (Box 13)
    - Chicago Council on Community Nursing (Box 13)
    - Community medical services: hospitals (Box 13)
    - Education (Box 13)
    - Facts and figures (Box 13)
    - Foreign nurses (Box 13)
    - Health rehabilitation (Box 13)
    - Health studies (Box 13)
    - Inactive nurses (Box 13)
    - Kansas State surveys of nursing profession (Box 13)
    - Medical care (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
    - Nightingale Project, Eva vB. Hansl, 1954; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Organizations (Box 13)
    - Part-time nursing (Box 13)
    - Patients (Box 13)
    - Practical nurses (Box 13)
    - Public health nurses, New York City strike, 1966 (Box 13)
    - Refresher course (Box 13)
    - Research (Box 13)
    - Returnees (Box 13)
    - Shortages (Box 13)
    - Staffing (Box 13)
    - Supply, Peterson (Box 13)
    - Training (Box 13)
    - U.S. public health statistics and analysis (Box 13)
    - Vacancies, unmet needs (Box 13)
    - Visiting nurses (Box 13)
  - Occupational outlook series, United States Department of Labor (Box 13)
  - Occupational pamphlets of the Institute of Occupations, 1935 (Box 13)
  - Occupational therapy (Box 13)
  - Oceanology - Sea Grant Colleges (Box 13)
  - Odd jobs (Box 13)
  - Ombudsman (Box 13)
  - Organizations, women's (Box 13)
  - Painters, women (Box 13)
  - Personnel (Box 13)
  - Philosophy, women in (Box 13)
  - Photographers (Box 13)
  - Physicists (Box 13)
  - Placement, job (Box 13)
  - Psychology (Box 13)
  - Publishing (Box 13)
  - Radio, women in (Box 13)
  - Retailing (Box 13)
  - Science
    - General (Box 13)
    - Chemistry and phystics (Box 13)
    - Scholarships in (Box 13)
    - Space technology (Box 13)
  - Sculptors, women as (Box 13)
  - Search for talent (Box 13)
  - Secretary - "Analysis of the Genus Secretary" (Box 13)
  - Social sciences, field work (Box 13)
  - Social work, women in (Box 13)
  - Sororities, college (Box 13)
  - Sports (Box 13)
  - Teaching - Partnership Teaching Program (Box 13)
  - Technicians (Box 14)
  - Telephone workers, women (Box 14)
  - Theatrical producers (Box 14)
  - Travel agents (Box 14)
  - Urban renewal (Box 14)
  - Veterinarian (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
- Part time employment
  - Articles (Box 14)
  - Atomic Energy Project (Box 14)
  - Helen Baker and Hazel Kyrk (Box 14)
  - Bibliography (Box 14)
  - Case histories (Box 14)